Guide to the Tunis F. Dean Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Tunis F. Dean papers
1886-1930
GEN MSS 797
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
17.25
(27 boxes)
The Tunis F. Dean Papers consist of Dean's correspondence files, some of his business and financial papers, some printed ephemera, fourteen scrapbooks, and a small group of photographs. Series I holds correspondence, both personal and professional, including letters from a number of actors and theater managers, particularly those in the Belasco theater organization. Series II holds a small group of personal papers, including a scrapbook devoted to the death of Dean's mother Catherine. Series III holds financial and other records of productions with which Dean was involved, starring actresses Blanche Bates, Frances Starr, and Leonore Ulric, among others. Also here are thirteen scrapbooks containing clippings and ephemera from Dean's career and the theatre world in general. While the collection is strong in theatre management, particularly regarding the trials and finances surrounding theatrical tours, it is perhaps equally important for the wealth of personal correspondence that reveals Dean's extensive network of friends and male lovers, and on-going relationship with the Catholic church.
Dean, Tunis F. (Tunis Ferdinand), 1865-1939
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Carmen D. Valentino on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, August 2006.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
The Tunis Dean Papers (*T-Mss 1939-002), at the Billy Rose Theatre Division, New York Public Library for the Performing Arts, holds a collection of similar correspondence, manuscripts, account books, photographs, clippings, scrapbooks, and other papers, which were gifts from Katherine C. Dean in 1937 and 1939.
Tunis F. Dean
Tunis Ferdinand Anthony Dean was the first of ten children of Irish immigrants William Henry Dean (died circa 1892) and Catherine Whalen Dean (circa 1848-1914), and was born either in Columbus or Indianapolis, Indiana. The date of his birth appears to have been March 3rd, 1865, as supported by his 1896 passport application and in the 1910 and 1930 federal census reports. However, the year variously appears as 1867 (in the 1900 federal census), 1869 (on his 1912 life insurance application), 1870 (on the 1915 dance program from his 45th birthday fete), and 1871 (in his 1939 obituaries in the New York and Baltimore papers).
Raised in Indianapolis, Dean entered the theatre business as an employee of William Hayden English (1822-1896), a noted politician who owned the English Opera House on the city's Monument Circle. He was hired away in 1885 by visiting impresario Patrick Harris, who took him to Baltimore to manage his theaters including the Academy of Music there. In 1890 Dean partnered with Harris and Harris's brother-in-law Richard Britton to form Harris, Britton and Dean, proprietors of a chain of theaters between Minneapolis and Baltimore featuring popular-priced entertainments. The firm continued on for only a few years following Harris's death in 1890, and Dean remained as manager of the Academy of Music when it was taken over by the Philadelphia firm of Nixon and Zimmerman in 1895. Aside from his affiliation with Samuel F. Nixon (1848-1918), Dean worked in Pittsburgh with Harry Davis (1861-1940), and, for a large part of his career, as a road manager, press agent, and personal representative with New York's great impresario David Belasco (1853-1931), his organization, and his company of actors: Dean handled Mrs. Leslie Carter, Frances Starr, Sarah Truax, and David Warfield, among others, as well as Blanche Bates, who became a personal friend. Perhaps the Belasco actress with whom he was most closely associated was Lenore Ulric (1892-1970), as he managed her tours of Tiger Rose, The Son-Daughter, The Gold Diggers, Kiki, and Lulu Belle between 1918 and 1926, and arranged her endorsements of products including perfume and jewelry. Toward the end of his career Dean worked with the actors Fanny Brice and Lionel Barrymore. Not just active the in theatre, Dean apparently invented a system to extract gold and silver from sea water, according to an article in the November 9, 1912, issue of Mining World.
After her husband's death, Catherine Dean moved to Baltimore and established a household (supported by Tunis Dean) through which revolved Dean and his siblings, at least four of whom also had careers in theatre management: Walter P. Dean (circa 1868-1909), Rose Dean Reaves (circa 1874-1895), Julia Dean Batten Hyland (circa 1876-1912), Katherine (Kate) Cecilia Dean (circa 1877-1950), Edward J. Dean (circa 1880-1912), and William Francis Dean (circa 1884-1904). Their home was a popular stopping place for the theatre community, as evidenced by the tributes received and national press coverage granted Catherine Dean at her death in 1914.
By all accounts debonair and creatively well-dressed (one obituary headline read "Veteran Theatrical Manager Was Colorful Figure Here Years Ago -- Noted Far And Wide for His Bizarre Clothes"), Tunis Dean was briefly engaged to the actress Anna Boyd in 1895, but never married. While his correspondence files reveal that he left broken hearts (both female and male) in cities and towns across the United States, they also show that he was extremely generous to his friends, colleagues, clients, and lovers, and regularly supported the businesses of florists everywhere. He died in Spring Valley, Rockland County, New York, on April 21, 1939, and was buried in the Dean family lot in Baltimore's New Cathedral Cemetery. In 1914 Dean had commissioned for the lot a granite obelisk twenty feet in height and a set of headstones for his mother and siblings; none of the monuments, including his, display life dates.
Scope and Contents
The Tunis F. Dean Papers consist of Dean's correspondence files, some of his business and financial papers, some printed ephemera, fourteen scrapbooks, and a small group of photographs. Series I holds correspondence, both personal and professional, including letters from a number of actors and theater managers, particularly those in the Belasco theater organization. Series II holds a small group of personal papers, including a scrapbook devoted to the death of Dean's mother Catherine. Series III holds financial and other records of productions with which Dean was involved, starring actresses Blanche Bates, Frances Starr, and Leonore Ulric, among others. Also here are thirteen scrapbooks containing clippings and ephemera from Dean's career and the theatre world in general. While the collection is strong in theatre management, particularly regarding the trials and finances surrounding theatrical tours, it is perhaps equally important for the wealth of personal correspondence that reveals Dean's extensive network of friends and male lovers, and on-going relationship with the Catholic church. The preservation of this documentation, particularly that surrounding his homosexual world, is remarkable especially considering that Dean was necessarily peripatetic for much of his adult life.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into three series: I. Correspondence, 1886-1930; II. Personal Papers, 1896-1929; and III. Theatre Records and Ephemera, 1887-1927.
Gay men -- United States; Theatrical managers -- United States; Theater -- United States; Business records; Condoms; Portrait photographs; Scrapbooks; Telegrams; LGBTQ resource; Bates, Blanche, 1873-1941; Beegle, May, d. 1943; Belasco, David, 1853-1931; Biedler, H. H. (Hampson Hubert), 1854-1921; Bookbinder, Herman R.; Curry, Thomas A. (Thomas Albert); Dean, Tunis F. (Tunis Ferdinand), 1865-1939; Duse, Eleonora, 1858-1924; Jardon, Dorothy, 1883-1966; Leishear, Mary S.; Pickford, Mary, 1892-1979; McCaull, Charles D.; Moore, Alexander Pollock, 1867-1930; Nixon-Nirdlinger, Samuel F., 1848-1918; Quinlan, Elizabeth C., 1863-1947; Roeder, Benjamin F., -1943; Shook, Harry Dean; Starr, Frances; Truax, Sarah, 1873-1958; Ulric, Lenore, 1892-1970; Wilken, William L.; Academy of Music (Baltimore, Md.); Belasco Theatre (New York, N.Y.); Grand Opera House (Pittsburgh, Pa.)
- Correspondence, 1886-1930; Series I; 10; (10 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I is arranged alphabetically by correspondent, followed by folders of chronologically filed general correspondence, telegrams, and greeting cards. A description of the papers provided by the vendor appears in the first folder of Box 1.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I contains ten linear feet of correspondence, primarily incoming letters from friends, colleagues, and business associates, with some copies of Dean's replies. The hundreds of letters and telegrams from the more than dozen administrators in the Belasco organization, including Herman Bookbinder, Tom Curry, C. D. McCaull, and B. F. Roeder, were kept as a group under the heading of Belasco Theatre. Also there are several hundred letters and telegrams from David Belasco himself, with many revealing his personal affection for Dean. Another of Dean's close professional relationships was with Samuel F. Nixon (born Samuel F. Nirdlinger) and his family, who made their home in Atlantic City, New Jersey. Of special interest in his folder are two typed carbon copies of an unsigned, threatening, and anti-Semitic letter, which were postmarked on May 27, 1917, in Pittsburgh, and sent to Nixon at his home address and work addresses; among other insults, the writer insinuated that Nixon would have only one more year to live.
  In addition to letters from management, the correspondence files hold letters from theatre stars including the actress Dorothy Jardon and Dean's long-time friend Blanche Bates and her husband George Creel, a journalist who was head of the United States Committee on Public Information during World War I. Also here is a folder of telegrams sent between Dean and Mary Pickford that detail her unsuccessful attempt to hire him as her business manager; the telegrams are followed by a stream of letters from Pickford's legal counsel. Their correspondence shows that some acquaintances in the newspaper business became personal friends, such as Emanuel Daniel, R. J. Farrell, Howard Shelley, and Alexander Pollock Moore, the publisher of the Pittsburgh Leader who married the actress Lillian Russell. Another close friend was the pioneering retailer Elizabeth C. Quinlan, founder of the Young-Quinlan Company in Minneapolis, the first women's ready-to-wear store west of the Mississippi River.
  There are several folders of letters from male lovers, such as Leo Climax in Cleveland, Joseph Kavitz in Springfield, Massachusetts, the otherwise unidentified George C. W. (with the Omaha Daily News, who enclosed his bawdy poem of 1918, "Ballade of Ye Gorgeous Nighte wt [sic] Ye Gorgeous Knighte"), and "Marion" in St. Louis, as well as a single plaintive note, enclosing a photograph, from Elmer Larson of Indianapolis (in Box 7, dated October 18, 1920). Aside from his sister Katherine, family members in the correspondence files include Dean's cousins Madge Dean Thompson, Ella and Rose Ferry, and Mary T. Dean, and niece Rosemary Batten. There is also correspondence from "nephews" Eugene Davis and Walter Dean Rogers (addressing letters to their "Uncle Tunis" and "Aunt Katherine" but their relationship to the Dean family is unknown), and Harry Dean Shook, who variously appears, or is described by Dean to others, as his nephew, cousin, roommate, chauffeur, companion, valet, co-worker, and son. Many, but not all, of the letters and telegrams exchanged between them are addressed by Shook to "Dear Dad" and by Dean to "Dear Son," and Dean often signed his messages to Shook, "Love, Dad." What is clear is that Shook was also on the payroll of the Belasco organization and occasionally lived with Dean and his sister Katherine at their homes in Baltimore and on New York's Staten Island; in the 1930 federal census, Shook is described as Dean's nephew, aged 38, and born in Connecticut.
  The series ends with five linear feet of unsorted chronologically arranged correspondence, which holds letters from a wide variety of personal and professional contacts, seven folders of letters specifically related to theatre business (largely technical matters of touring: reservations, trains, hotels, etc.), a few folders of chronologically arranged telegrams, both incoming and outgoing, covering all subjects, and a group of greeting and holiday cards.
  While nearly all of the letters are addressed to Dean, some are addressed to his sister Katherine and to Harry Shook, both working as theatrical managers; the letters remain interfiled with those to Dean.
  - Vendor description, [2006] (Box 1)
  - Bates, Blanche, and family, 1910-1925, undated; 2 (Box 1)
  - Batten, Rosemary, 1914-1915 (Box 1)
  - Bauer, Alfred, 1921, undated (Box 1)
  - Beegle, May, 1913-23 (Box 1)
  - Belasco Theatre (Organization: New York, N.Y.)
    - Belasco, David, 1918-1930, undated; 7 (Box 1)
    - Bookbinder, Herman R., 1918-1928, undated; 4 (Box 1)
    - Cubitt, William C., 1923-1925 (Box 1)
    - Curry, Thomas A., 1917-1926; 2 (Box 1)
    - Dodge, Wendell Phillips, 1918 (Box 1)
    - Hartmann, Louis, 1919 (Box 1)
    - Head, Alfred, 1921-1928 (Box 1)
    - Howard, W. D., 1918-1923 (Box 1)
    - McCaull, Charles D., 1921-1926; 3 (Box 2)
    - McGarry, Joseph A., 1920-1926 (Box 2)
    - Massen, Louis, 1918-1922 (Box 2)
    - Roeder, Benjamin Franklin, 1907-1928, undated; 6 (Box 2)
    - Smyth, W. G. (William G.) and Sydney Armstrong, 1909-1921; 3 (Box 2)
    - Symon, Burk, 1922-1926, undated (Box 2)
    - Wilken, William L., and Julia, 1922-1926, undated; 2 (Box 2)
    - Belasco staff, miscellaneous, 1909-1926; 2 (Box 3)
  - Biedler, H. H. (Hampson Hubert), 1912-1921 (Box 3)
  - Black, Jotham F. and Fredericka, 1913-1919 (Box 3)
  - Blitzsten, Lionel, 1921, undated (Box 3)
  - Bloomingdale, Karl, 1919-1922, undated (Box 3)
  - Bollinger, Veolante Lovingston, 1919-1920 (Box 3)
  - Carruthers, Mabel, 1916-1924 (Box 3)
  - Catholic Actors' Guild of America, 1920-1924 (Box 3)
  - Chapin, William V. and Mary Worth, 1920-1926, undated (Box 3)
  - Climax, Leo, 1922-1923 (Box 3)
  - Collins, Emile, 1925-1926 (Box 3)
  - Creel, George
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: Bates, Blanche
  - Curry, Louise, 1912-1913 (Box 3)
  - Daniel, Emanuel, 1917-1921 (Box 3)
  - Davis, Eugene G., 1917-1923 (Box 3)
  - Dean, Catherine (letters from Tunis Dean), 1908, 1914 (Box 3)
  - Dean, Katherine Cecilia, 1914-1928, undated; 2 (Box 3)
  - Dean, Mary T., 1919-1922 (Box 3)
  - Dean, Walter, 1890 Jan 6 (Box 3)
  - Dean relatives, miscellaneous, 1910-1923 (Box 3)
  - Dunn, Emma, 1917-1924 (Box 3)
  - Dupree, Minnie, 1920-1922, undated (Box 3)
  - Farrell, R. J., 1918-1923 (Box 3)
  - Ferry, Ella M. and Rose, 1914-1925 (Box 3)
  - Findlay, Cora, 1919-1924, undated (Box 3)
  - Griswold, Russell, 1915 (Box 3)
  - Harry Davis Enterprises Company, 1902, 1914-1926 (Box 3)
  - Hartley, Randolph, 1922 (Box 3)
  - Hering, Walter, 1914-1927 (Box 3)
  - Holmes, Walter G., 1921-1926 (Box 3)
  - Jardon, Dorothy, 1914-1922, undated; 4 (Box 3)
  - Kavitz, Joseph, 1920-1922; 3 (Box 4)
  - Kean, Thomas, 1922, 1926 (Box 4)
  - Leishear, Mary S. (Mamie), 1913-1926, undated (Box 4)
  - Leslie, Brownie, 1917-1926 (Box 4)
  - Lewenthal, Fred and Abe, 1918-1925 (Box 4)
  - Longley, Mary T., 1920-1926 (Box 4)
  - Love, Thomas M.
    See: Samuel F. Nixon
  - M'Cann, W. E., 1916-1918, undated (Box 4)
  - McLaughlin, Leonard, and mother, 1916-1917 (Box 4)
  - Meighan, Thomas, 1924 (Box 4)
  - Moore, Alexander Pollock, 1914-1922 (Box 4)
  - Nathan, Ella C., 1922-1923 (Box 4)
  - Neville, Julia, 1917-1925 (Box 4)
  - Nixon, Samuel F., 1911-1917, undated (Box 4)
  - Nixon-Nirdlinger, Tessa Theresa B., 1913-1922, undated; 2 (Box 4)
  - Oberfelder, Sydney, 1922 (Box 4)
  - O'Reilly, James B., 1920-1925 (Box 4)
  - Otis [?], Etta, 1925 (Box 4)
  - Otis, William L., 1920-1925; 5 (Box 4)
  - Parsons, Murray, 1920-1921; 2 (Box 5)
  - Pickford, Mary, 1917-1918 (Box 5)
  - Quinlan, Elizabeth C., 1912-1926, undated; 2 (Box 5)
  - Roak, James C., 1914-1918 (Box 5)
  - Robson, May, 1922 (Box 5)
  - Rogers, Walter Dean, 1914-1925 (Box 5)
  - Shelley, Howard, 1918-1919 (Box 5)
  - Shook, Harry Dean, 1920-1928, undated; 2 (Box 5)
  - Smith, William, 1918-1921 (Box 5)
  - Starr, Frances, 1917-1926 (Box 5)
  - Steiner, Emma R., 1918 Oct 30 (Box 5)
  - Stoddard, Emma V., 1923 (Box 5)
  - Taylor, Nellie Rosilla, 1921-1926, undated (Box 5)
  - Thompson, Madge Dean, 1923 (Box 5)
  - Thorn, John, 1919-1923 (Box 5)
  - Truax, Sarah, 1923-1924 (Box 5)
  - Ulric, Lenore, 1919-1926, undated (Box 5)
  - Ulric, Ray R., 1920-1923, undated (Box 5)
  - Unruh, William Grayson, 1922-1923 (Box 5)
  - Vanderbilt, Gertrude, 1923-1926 (Box 5)
  - W., George C., 1918-1920 (Box 5)
  - Weiler, Sidney
    See: Bloomingdale, Karl
  - Whitton, Helen Stafford, 1922-1924 (Box 5)
  - Wilson, Marie Murray, 1911-1923, undated (Box 5)
  - Young, Hugh H., 1917-1926, undated (Box 5)
  - [Unidentified], Marion, 1919-1920 (Box 5)
  - Letters, outgoing, 1908-1925 (Box 5)
  - General correspondence, personal and professional, 1886-1919; 15 (Box 6)
  - General correspondence, personal and professional, 1920-1922 Mar; 13 (Box 7)
  - General correspondence, personal and professional, 1922 Apr-1925; 14 (Box 8)
  - General correspondence, personal and professional, 1926-1927; 4 (Box 9)
  - General correspondence, personal and professional, undated; 9 (Box 9)
  - General correspondence, theatre business, 1906-1928, undated; 6 (Box 10)
  - Empty envelopes, 3 (Box 10)
  - Telegrams, incoming, chronological, 1906-1927, undated; 6 (Box 10)
  - Telegrams outgoing, chronological, 1920-1928 (Box 10)
  - Greeting cards, invitations, and announcements, 1914-1926; 2 (Box 10)
- Personal Papers, 1896-1929; Series II; 1.5; (2 boxes)
  The series contains miscellaneous papers including Dean's insurance and tax records, calling cards and letter paper, some personal bills, and ephemera such as a license for his pet dog, storage receipts, and copies of a piece of sheet music, "The Tunisian March Two Step" by Frederick W. Foote, which was dedicated to Dean. Also here is evidence of his engagement to actress Anna Boyd, his metallurgical inventions, and an order for the family cemetery monuments. A single scrapbook is devoted to the death of his mother Catherine.
  - Business cards and personal letter paper, undated (Box 11)
  - Business cards of others, undated (Box 11)
  - Catholic literature, 1917-1927 (Box 11)
  - Condoms (2), circa 1923 (Box 11)
  - Insurance papers, 1903-1927; 10 (Box 11)
  - Holiday card, sheet music, birthday program, and Testimonial Benefit program, 1896-1917 (Box 11)
  - Letter paper (unused) from hotels and theaters, undated (Box 11)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 11)
    General note
    One print of Dean, three of others (unidentified)
  - Portfolio/blotter, undated (Box 11)
  - Tax and financial papers, 1903-1929; 2 (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous ephemera, bills, receipts, notes, 7 (Box 11)
  - Scrapbook of obituaries, telegrams, cards, and notes regarding death of Catherine Dean, 1914 (Box 12)
- Theatre Records and Ephemera, 1887-1927; Series III; 5.75; (14 boxes)
  Series III is organized into three subseries: Production Files, Other Records, and Scrapbooks.
  The series holds a group of files from productions with which Dean was associated as a manager or publicist, files of miscellaneous press releases and essays, and a series of scrapbooks that document his career. The files hold cast lists, financial statements, and miscellaneous documents and printed ephemera. Press releases deal with productions and Dean's own self-promotion, as well as his thoughts on the topics of knickers, the future of motion pictures, and the author Hall Caine. A set of oversize photographs of Leonore Ulric include stills of the cast of Lulu Belle (1926); two short strips of pink-tinted Cine-Positive nitrate motion picture film (seven frames in all) with images of Ulric were removed to cold storage. The compiler of the thirteen scrapbooks covering Dean's career is unknown but was likely Dean, his sister Katherine, and/or their mother; three of the scrapbooks concern performances by actress Sarah Truax. The scrapbook devoted to the actress Eleonora Duse's American tour of 1902-1903 may not be related to Dean, and may have been created by a contemporary, the actor Harry C. Bruninghaus, whose stamp appears inside the front cover. Two boxes at the end of the series hold folded newspaper clippings, primarily from the early twentieth century.
  - Production files
    Arranged chronologically
    - Blanche Bates productions, 1905-1912 (Box 13)
    - Mrs. Leslie Carter productions, 1906 (Box 13)
    - Rose of the Ranch, 1906 (Box 13)
    - Frances Starr productions, 1911-1920 (Box 13)
    - Tiger Rose, 1918-1919 (Box 13)
    - The Son-Daughter, 1920-1921 (Box 13)
    - Call the Doctor, 1921 (Box 13)
    - The Gold Diggers, 1921-1923 (Box 13)
    - Mary Mary Quite Contrary, 1923 (Box 13)
    - Kiki, 1923-1924 (Box 13)
    - Lionel Barrymore Company, 1924 (Box 13)
    - Ladies of the Evening, 1924-1925 (Box 13)
    - The Dove, 1924-1927 (Box 13)
    - Canon's Dutch, 1925 (Box 13)
    - Fanny Brice Company, 1926 (Box 13)
    - Lulu Belle, 1926 (Box 13)
    - Lily Sue, 1926-1927 (Box 13)
    - Christmas pantomime, undated (Box 13)
  - Other records
    - Journal, with notes, tickets, clippings, regarding benefit performances, 1911-1915 (Box 13)
    - Legal papers, 1890-1924 (Box 13)
    - Photographs of Leonore Ulric, 1926, undated
    - Press releases and essays, undated; 4 (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous ephemera, press lists, notes, 3 (Box 13)
  - Scrapbooks
    Containing newspaper clippings on theatre business and Tunis Dean's career
    - Primarily covering Academy of Music, Baltimore, 1887-1888 (Box 14)
    - Covering Albaugh's Opera House (1890), and Academy of Music (1895-1896), 1890-1896 (Box 15)
    - Covering Academy of Music, Baltimore, 1890 (Box 16)
    - Covering Academy of Music, Baltimore, 1894-1895 (Box 16)
    - Covering Pittsburgh theaters, 1890, 1903 (Box 17)
    - Covering various performances, including many by Sarah Truax, 1891-1902 (Box 18)
    - Baltimore theaters (1895), and Grand Opera House, Pittsburgh (1903-1904) concerning Sarah Truax, 1895, 1903-1904 (Box 19)
    - Primarily covering Harris' Academy of Music, Baltimore, with pages of receipts and documents from stay in Pittsburgh (1903), 1896, 1903 (Box 20)
      Includes pages on Dean's tenth anniversary testimonial benefit, May 7, 1896
    - Covering tours by Melbourne MacDowell and Fanny Davenport, 1896-1897 (Box 21)
    - Covering tour of John Philip Sousa's The Bride Elect, 1898 (Box 21)
    - Covering Grand Opera House and Sarah Truax, 1901-1902 (Box 22)
    - Covering Eleonora Duse's American tour, 1902-1903 (Box 23)
      Stamp of Harry Bruninghaus inside front cover
    - Covering Blanche Bates in The Girl of the Golden West, 1905 (Box 24)
    - Covering Lenore Ulric in Lulu Belle, 1927 (Box 24)
    - Newspaper clippings, unsorted and unfolded, 34 (Box 25–26)
- OVERSIZE
  - Shelley, Howard (in Series I), 1918-1919 (Box 27)
  - W., George C. (in Series I), 1918-1920 (Box 27)
  - Photographs of Leonore Ulric (in Series III), 1926, undated (Box 27)
  - Miscellaneous ephemera (in Series III) (Box 27)